Guide to the Concerned Residents of the Youghiogheny Records, 1968-2004 AIS.2004.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Mill Service, Inc. and Environmental Pollution, IV.
  - Correspondence, Mill Service - Internal and Political, 1972-1991 (Box 11, Folder 36-39)
  - Customers (of Mill Service, Inc.) (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Dike Stability (Box 11, Folder 41)
  - Discharge Monitoring Reports, 1980-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Domestic Well Survey - Mill Service (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Economic Impairment Study (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - EPA Organic and Inorganic Analysis Report (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - EPA Site Inspection of Mill Service (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - EPA Toxic Inventory (Box 12, Folder 6-8)
  - Evaluation of Chemistry and Industrial Processes at Mill Service (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Exposure Information Reports (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
  - Fact Sheets (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Financial Responsibility Documents, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Furnace Dusts (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Hazardous Waste Facilities Plan Comments (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Hazardous Waste Inspection Report (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Hazard Code - Waste Transport (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Hazardous Waste Types (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Hydrogeological Report, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Hydrogeological Assessment for #5 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Hydrogeological Report for #6, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Impoundment #5 Inspections (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Impoundment #5 Leachate Characterization (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Impoundment #6 Application (Box 12, Folder 24-28)
  - Impoundment #6 Groundwater Monitoring System Installation (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Impoundment #6 Information (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Impoundment #6 Inspection (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Incentives for New Facility (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Industrial Waste Disposal at Permitted Sites (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Interim Operating Guidance (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Lime Stabilization (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Maps (Box 13, Folder 8-12)
  - Mill Service Background by David Free (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Mill Service Blasting Permit (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Mill Service Bulger Violations (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Mill Service Compliance Problems (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Mill Service Employee Absence Record (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Mill Service Inspection Reports, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Mill Service History by Diana Steck (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Mill Service Mining, Blasting Information (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Mill Service Permit "File #2" (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - NUS-TDD #F3-8308-23 Report (Site inspection) (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Pathways (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Permits (Box 13, Folder 24-31)
  - Permits (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Pollutional Study of Mill Service (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Post-Closure Plan #5 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
  - Pre-blast survey (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Quality Assurance - Review for Organics (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - RCRA Facility Assessment - Phase II Report (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Replies to Mill Service (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Reports (Box 14, Folder 10-13)
  - Sampling and Analysis Procedure #6 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Sanitary Survey Forms (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Summary of Penetrometer Tests (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Tank Information #4 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Toxic Chemical Release Inventory and Report (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Transporter Contingency Plan (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Waste Characteristics #6 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Waste Generators (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Water Storage and Hauling (Box 14, Folder 22-23)
  - Water Analysis Report (Box 14, Folder 24)
- Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection (DEP), formerly Department of Environmental Resources (DER), V.
  The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection is the government agency responsible for regulating the operations of businesses that have an impact on the environment. They maintain a website at: http://www.dep.state.pa.us. The DEP has the authority to issue, suspend, and revoke permits for storage and treatment of various kinds of wastes and for other related operations. In this role and as the host of the Environmental Hearing Board until 1988, the formerly named Department of Environmental Resources was the main agency that CRY dealt with in its mission to close down Mill Service's waste storage site in Yukon. The Department changed its name to the Department of Environmental Protection in 1995. These files hold correspondence between DER officials, Mill Service personnel, CRY members, and others; records of public meetings held between DER and CRY; and information on various operations conducted by the DER. It overlaps Series IV somewhat in its scope.
  - Correspondence: Various (Box 14, Folder 25-26)
  - Correspondence: CRY and its members (Box 14, Folder 27-32)
  - Correspondence: Duritsa, Charles and Bender, Carl (Box 14, Folder 33-35)
  - Correspondence: Mill Service, Inc. (Box 14, Folder 36-39)
  - Correspondence: Attorneys for CRY (Phelps, Gail and Ging, Robert) (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence: Politicians (Box 15, Folder 3-6)
  - Draft Risk Assessment for Hazardous Waste Incineration (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Impoundment #6 - Inspection (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
  - Meetings - CRY and DER, 1987-1994 (Box 15, Folder 10-15)
  - Municipal Waste Regulations (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Permits (Box 15, Folder 17-18)
  - Press Releases and Clippings (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Reports (Box 15, Folder 20-23)
  - Soil Information (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - Standards (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Waste Analysis and Classification (Box 15, Folder 26-27)
- Litigation, VI.
  These records document CRY's legal challenges to Mill Service, Inc.'s waste disposal operations in southwest Pennsylvania from 1986 through 1994. One of the main cases was first brought to the Environmental Hearing Board (EHB), a distinct judicial arm of the DER (now DEP), by CRY and Westmoreland County to challenge the legitimacy of permits granted by the DER to Mill Service for waste disposal, construction, and mining. Another main case represented was brought by Yukon residents petitioning for relief or compensation from Mill Service for deleterious effects to health and property values (multiple complaints were soon consolidated). Suits were also filed by Mill Service and the DER against CRY and its members in response to disruptive demonstrations staged near Mill Service and DER properties. Though CRY's challenges to Mill Service's permits resulted in periods of temporary suspension for the company, the allegations of unlawful conduct were never resolved in CRY's favor, and a protracted series of appeals was finally abandoned in 1994 when CRY's finances did not allow for counsel. The DER ultimately approved all Mill Service operations based on the Consent Order and amendments.
  Appeals of EHB decisions are heard in Pa. Commonwealth Court. Challenges and petitions for relief were heard variously in the Courts of Common Pleas of Westmoreland and Allegheny Counties, the United States District Court for the Western District of Pennsylvania in Pittsburgh, and the Supreme Court of Pennsylvania. Not all actions were pursued to definitive decision; several were dismissed or dropped after relatively short periods of time. Legal briefs, complaints, motions and appeals are arranged chronologically and secondarily by docket or case number. In instances of transfer between courts, or consolidation, several different case or docket numbers may be assigned to a single general legal action. There is also a section of legal correspondence, mostly to and from CRY's attorneys: Gail Phelps until 1988, Robert J. Ging from 1988 to 1994.
  - Outline of EHB Appeal Process (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - Mill Service Consent Agreements with EPA/DER, 1975-1976 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - Consent Orders, Pa. DER v. Mill Service, Inc. Nos. 1406-07 C.D. 1985 in the Commonwealth Court of Pa.., May 24, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Amendment No. 1 to Consent Order and Adjudication, In the Matter of Mill Service, May 14, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Legal Statement to Support Pa.'s Final Authorization of the Hazardous Waste Management Program, October 1985 (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Babich (et al.) v. Mill Service (et al.). Civil Division No. 2070 of 1985 in the Court of Common Pleas of Westmoreland Co., 1985-1988 (Box 15, Folder 33-35)
  - Health Surveys- Kodrin, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Co. of Westmoreland V. Mill Service, No. 8075 of 1985 in Court of Common Please of Westmoreland Co., Complaint in Equity (Box 15, Folder 37)
  - Seaton v. Mill Service, No. 8107 of 1986 in the Civil Division of the Court of Common Pleas of Westmoreland Co. (Box 15, Folder 38)
  - Babich (et al.) v. Mill Service (et al.). C.A. No. 87-0210 in the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Pa., 1987-1989 (Box 15, Folder 39)
  - Copies of Pa. DER Permits (to Mill Service for Impoundment No. 6) Nos. 301071, E65-164, D-65-163, and (65) 65-84-8-2, August 6, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 40)
  - Notice of Appeal of Permits by CRY (et al.), in the matter of CRY v. Pa. DER before the EHB in the matter of Mill Service, Sept. 3, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 41)
  - Notice of Appeal of Permits by Westmoreland Co., Sept. 5, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - CRY (et al.) v. Mill Service in the Court of Common Pleas of Westmoreland Co., Complaint, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 43)
  - EHB No. 86-154-R (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - CRY, et al., v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, EHB No. 86-513-R (Consolidated with 86-438-R to 86-512-R), AND Westmoreland Co. v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, EHB No. 86-515-R, 1986-1990 (Box 16, Folder 2-7)
  - Mill Service v. Pa. DER (and CRY, intervener), EHB No. 86-514-R, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 8-10)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER (and Mill Service, intervener), EHB No. 89-113-F, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER, EHB No. 89-133-W (later consolidated EHB 89-513-R), 1989 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, EHB No. 86-513-MJ, 1990-1993 (Box 16, Folder 13-14)
  - Mill Service v. Pa. DER, EHB No. 87-438-R, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Steck v. Mill Service et al., No. 4646 of 1989, in the Court of Common Pleas of Westmoreland Co. (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Petition for Writ of Certorari by the Pa. DER, Docket No. 06105-1989 in the Civil Division, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny Co. (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Petition for Writ of Certorari by the Pa. DER, No. S.A. 2636-89 in the Civil Division, Statutory Appeals, Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny Co., 1989 (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Mill Service v. CRY (et al.), No. 7195 of 1989 in the Civil Division, Court of Common Pleas of Westmoreland Co., 1989-1991 (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, EHB Notice of Appeal, May 1989 (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, EHB No. 89-133-MJ, 1990-1993 (Box 16, Folder 21-22)
  - CRY and Westmoreland Co. v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, No. 458 C.D. 1993 and No. 501 C.D. 1993 in the Commonwealth Court of Pa., 1993-1994 (Box 16, Folder 23-24)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, No. 1986 C.D. 1993 in the Commonwealth Court of Pa., 1993-1994 (Box 16, Folder 25)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, No. 634 W.D. Allocatur Docket 1994 in the Supreme Court of Pa., 1994-1995 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER, No. 14 W.D. Appeal Docket 1995 in the Supreme Court of Pa. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - CRY et al. v. Mill Service, C.A. No. 90-0923 in U.S. District Court, 3rd Circuit, for Western District of Pa.., 1990 (Box 17, Folder 3-8)
  - CRY (et al.) v. Mill Service, No. 3078 of 1990 in the Court of Common Pleas of Westmoreland Co., 1990-1993 (Box 17, Folder 9-12)
  - Mill Service v. CRY (et al.) and Pa. DER, No. 2506 C.D. 1991 in the Commonwealth Court of Pa., 1992 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Mill Service v. CRY (et al.), No. 632 W.D. Allocatur Docket in the Supreme Court of Pa., 1992 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - CRY (et al.) v. Mill Service, No. 0005 W.D. Appeal Docket 1993 in the Supreme Court of Pa. (Box 17, Folder 15-17)
  - CRY et al. v. Mill Service and Pa. DER, No. 247 M.D. 1994 in the Supreme Court of Pa. (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER, Mill Service, petitioner, No. 621 W.D. Allocatur Docket 1995 in the Supreme Court of Pa. (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Notice of Appeal of Permit No. 301071 and Modification, Request for Public Hearing, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER, EHB No. 91-544-MJ, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - CRY (and Westmoreland Co). v. Pa. DER and Mill Service, EHB No. 92-106-MJ, 1992-1995 (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - Mill Service v. Pa. DER, EHB No. 92-251-MJ, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - CRY v. Pa. DER (and Mill Service), EHB No. 92-249-MJ, 1992-1993 (Box 17, Folder 24-27)
  - EHB Jan 1995 and DIB - Scurrilous Comments (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Property Tax Assessments/Appeals, 1990-1997 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - IRS Tax Assessment, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - Commonwealth of Pa. v. Frank Trputec, No. 00802 Pittsburgh, 1986 in the Superior Court of Pa., May 1987 (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - City of Coatesville v. Delaware Container Co., Nos. 88-1688, 88-1763, 88-1816 in the U.S. Court of Appeals, 3rd Circuit, Eastern District of Pa." Brief of Amicus Curiae" (Manderino and CRY, Pa. DER), 1987-1989 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - Envirotrol v. Paul Morack, et al., No. 1866-1991 in the Civil Div., Court of Common Pleas of Beaver Co. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Alice Water Protection Assoc. v. Commonwealth of Pa., Pa. DEP, and Amerikohl Mining, EHB No. 95-112-R, "Brief of Amicus Curiae" (CRY, et al.) (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Mill Service, Inc. Benefit Fee Case (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Ging Policy Legislation, 1989-1991 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Litigation Notes (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Public Interest Law Group (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Phelps, Gail (Box 18, Folder 10-12)
  - Correspondence: Ging, Robert (Box 18, Folder 13-27)
- News Releases and Clippings, VII.
  Media coverage of the group and its activities served to publicize CRY's mission, and was a primary factor in the group's effectiveness. The group put out news releases and kept copies of them, along with clippings and copies of articles and cartoons published in Western Pennsylvania regional newspapers, and local and national magazines. These clippings represent public perceptions of CRY and Mill Service, Inc., and chronicle key activities and events, including public protests, citizen actions, the process of legal petitions, and town meetings, as well as developments at Mill Service's Yukon site, from CRY's inception in 1985 through 2001. Other topics covered by the articles include a government investigation and reorganization of the State of Pennsylvania's Department of Environmental Resources (DER), and contemporary citizens' groups and legal actions aimed at environmental protection and clean-up nation-wide. The articles focus on environmental issues in the Appalachian region, notably the Youghiogheny River and Sewickley Creek watersheds. Files are arranged chronologically by year.
  - News Releases, 1985-1993 (Box 18, Folder 28-39)
  - News Clippings, 1984-1989 (Box 19, Folder 1-7)
  - News Clippings, 1990-1997 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
  - News Clippings, including Cartoons, undated (Box 20, Folder 7-11)
- Files from the office of Pa. Representative Manderino, VIII.
  CRY wrote to many politicians to raise awareness of their situation and garner support for their mission. They specifically sought to form relationships with state legislators, and State Representative James J. Manderino became one of their dedicated allies. He and his executive assistant Herman Mihalich (later a Representative himself) kept files pertaining to their dealings with and on behalf of CRY, and these are arranged alphabetically and later by subject. The photographs of the Mill Service site in the first part are generally in poor condition and with little identification.
  - Articles (News Clippings) (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Blasting Permit (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Bolk (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Casey, Governor and EPA - Letters to (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Citizens of Area (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Commission for Foreign Medical Graduates (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Consent Orders (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Court Cases (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - CRY (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - DER (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - EPA (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - Groundwater Remediation (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - Hazardous Waste Permit (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Health Department (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Health Study (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - Herman (Mihalich) (Box 21, Folder 17-18)
  - Insurance (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Lagoon #5 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Lagoon #6 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Maps (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Memos (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Mill Service (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
  - Mill Service Interim Status (Box 22, Folder 7-8)
  - Mill Service Permits (Box 22, Folder 9-12)
  - Miscellaneous/Yukon Acid Plant (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Pictures (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Press Releases (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Regulations (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Reports/Studies (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - RCRA Complaint (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Solid Waste Disposal Permit (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Surface Mining Permit (Box 23, Folder 3-4)
  - Acid Rain (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Chesapeake Bay (Cleanup) (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Coal (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Energy Partners/TAS Systems (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Education (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Incineration (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Landfill (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Low-Level Radioactive Disposal (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Municipal Waste Dumps (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - OSHA Right to Know (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Recycling (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Superfund (Box 23, Folder 16)
  - South Huntingdon Township (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Toxic Health Advisory Committee (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Waste Permits - Non-hazardous (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Westmoreland County (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Westmoreland County DA (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Wetlands (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Yukon Residents (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Yukon/South Huntingdon Water (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - CRY Activities: Yukon/Babich (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - CRY Activities: Mill Service Insurance Documents (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - CRY Activities: CRY Health Study (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - CRY Activities: CRY Mill Service (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - CRY Activities: CRY News Releases (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - CRY Activities: CRY Yukon (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - CRY Activities: Environmental Hearing Board (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Mill Service Blasting Operations (Box 25, Folder 8-12)
  - Environmental Studies- Water Studies (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - Environmental Studies- Pa. Potential Hazardous Sites - 1981 List (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Environmental Studies- 1981 Superfund EPA States Cooperative Agreements (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Environmental Studies- Armco (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Environmental Studies- Wetlands (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Docket #86-514-R (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Newspaper Clippings (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Commonwealth Court CD 1406-85 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Maps (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Bulger Consent Order (Box 25, Folder 22)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Sludge Samples (Box 25, Folder 23)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Complaint CA 87-0210 (Box 25, Folder 24)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Ellyn Weiss (research attorney) (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Plaintiff's Response to motion 12 B (1) (5) (6) (Box 25, Folder 26)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Mill Service Response to Motion 2-24-87 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Babich (Box 25, Folder 28)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Complaint 87-0210, Babich 86-1205 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Mill Service Insurance - Babich 86-1205 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- Mihalich, Herman (Box 25, Folder 31)
  - Litigation Against Mill Service, Inc.- David W. Free, Report (Box 25, Folder 32)
- Medical Records, IX.
  Medical records consist of laboratory and physician's reports, patient histories, signed doctor and patient statements, and correspondence concerning residents of Yukon, Pa., and surrounding areas, who believed they were suffering negative health consequences of exposure to pollutants. Reports deal with toxicology and tissue analysis, and the treatment of respiratory ailments, hepatitis, anemia, and cancers. Correspondence largely deals with patient and attorney requests for records, and patient and physician forms of consent, which qualified the reports for use as evidence in CRY's court proceedings. Copies of medical files were submitted to CRY attorney Robert Ging, Esq.
  In order to protect the privacy of individuals involved, and in compliance with the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA), these records are restricted and closed to researchers until further notice.
  - Medical Records [RESTRICTED] (Box 26)
- Posters, X.
  Homemade, hand-lettered signs and posters were used by CRY in protests and other activities. These include some montages of photographs taken by group members.
  - Posters (Box 26, Folder Oversize)
- Videotapes, XI.
  Most of these are damaged and need to be repaired before they can be viewed. Many of them are labeled as documenting group activities or as copies of television programs.
  - Videotapes (Box 27)